<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An act for the encouraging &amp; increasing of shipping and navigation</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82447</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E1108</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1075_16</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208537</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867483</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867483</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119796</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82447)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119796)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 160:E1075[16])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An act for the encouraging &amp; increasing of shipping and navigation</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 21, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Bill and Christopher Barker, Printers to the Kings most Excellent Majesty,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from general title page.</note>
                  <note>At head of caption: Anno XII. Caroli II. Regis.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F² .</note>
                  <note>Last word of first line of text: 'shipping'; first word of line below initial: 'strength'; last word of last full line of text of first page: 'or'.</note>
                  <note>Also includes: An act to prevent frauds and concealments of His Majesties customs and subsidies.</note>
                  <note>Issued separately with a general title page: 'Anno Regni Caroli II. Regis Angliæ, Scotiæ, Franciæ, &amp; Hiberniæ, duodecimo. At the Parliament begun at VVestminster, the five and twentieth day of April, an. Dom. 1660.'.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept 18".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Shipping --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Commerce --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119796:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Anno Regni CAROLI II.</p>
            <p>REGIS <hi>Angliae, Scotiae, Franciae,</hi> &amp; <hi>Hiberniae,</hi> DUODECIMO.</p>
            <p>At the Parliament begun at <hi>VVeſtminſter,</hi> the Five and twentieth day of <hi>April, An. Dom.</hi> 1660.</p>
            <p>In the Twelfth year of the Reign of our moſt Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Sovereign Lord <hi>CHARLES,</hi> By the Grace of God, of <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> King, Defender of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Bill</hi> and <hi>Chriſtopher Barker,</hi> Printers to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty, 1660.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum Privilegio.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119796:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119796:2"/>
            <head>Anno XII. CAROLI II. Regis. AN ACT FOR THE Encouraging &amp; Increaſing OF SHIPPING AND NAVIGATION.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the increaſe of Shipping, and encouragement of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigation of this Nation, wherein, under the good Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence and Protection of God, the Wealth, Safety, and Strength of this Kingdom is ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, Be it Enacted by the Kings moſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Majeſty, and by the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in this preſent Parliament aſſembled, and the Authority thereof, That from and after the Firſt day of <hi>December,</hi> One thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſix hundred and ſixty, and from thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward, no Goods or Commodities whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall be Imported into, or Exported out of any Lands, Iſlands, Plantations, or
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119796:3"/> Territories to His Majeſty belonging, or in His poſſeſsion, or which may hereafter belong unto, or be in the poſſeſſion of His Majeſty, His Heirs and Succeſſors, in <hi>Aſia, Africa,</hi> or <hi>America,</hi> in any other ſhip or ſhips, Veſſel or Veſſels whatſoever, but in ſuch ſhips or Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels as do truly and without fraud belong one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the people of <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>Wales,</hi> or Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> or are of the built of, and belonging to any the ſaid Lands, Iſlands, Plantations, or Territories, as the Proprietors and right Owners thereof, and whereof the Maſter and three fourths of the Marriners at leaſt are <hi>Engliſh,</hi> under the penalty of the Forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Loſs of all the Goods and Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities which ſhall be Imported into, or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported out of any the aforeſaid places in any other Ship or Veſſel, as alſo of the Ship or Veſſel, with all its Guns, Furniture, Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ckle, Ammunition and Apparel, one third part thereof to His Majeſty, His Heirs and Succeſſors, one third part to the Governor of ſuch Land, Plantation, Iſland, or Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, where ſuch default ſhall be committed, in caſe the ſaid Ship or Goods be there ſeized, or otherwiſe that third part alſo to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, His Heirs and Succeſſors, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther third part to him or them who ſhall Seize, Inform, or ſue for the ſame in any Court of Record, by Bill, Information, Plaint, or other Action, wherein no Eſſoign, Protection, or Wager of Law ſhall be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed; and all Admirals, and other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders at Sea of any the ſhips of War, or other ſhip, having Commiſſion from His Majeſty, or from His Heirs or Succeſſors,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119796:3"/> are hereby Authorized and ſtrictly required to ſeize and bring in as Prize all ſuch Ships or Veſſels, as ſhall have offended contrary hereunto, and deliver them to the Court of Admiralty, there to be proceeded againſt; and in caſe of condemnation, one moyety of ſuch Forfeitures ſhall be to the uſe of ſuch Admirals or Commanders and their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, to be divided and proportioned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them according to the Rules and Orders of the Sea in caſe of Ships ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Prize, and the other Moyety to the uſe of His Majeſty, His Heirs and Succeſſors.</p>
            <p>And be it Enacted, That no Alien or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon not born within the Allegiance of Our Soveraign Lord the King, His Heirs and Succeſſors, or Naturalized, or made a frée Denizen, ſhall from and after the Firſt day of <hi>February,</hi> which ſhall be in the year of Our Lord One thouſand ſix hundred ſixty one, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe the Trade or Occupation of a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant or Factor in any the ſaid Places, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on pain of the Forfeiture and Loſs of all his Goods and Chattels, or which are in his poſſeſsion, one third to His Majeſty His Heirs and Succeſſors, one third to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of the Plantation, where ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhall ſo offend, and the other third to him or them that ſhall inform or ſue for the ſame in any of His Majeſties Courts in the Plantation, where ſuch offence ſhall be committed: And all Governors of the ſaid Lands, Iſlands, Plantations or Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and every of them are hereby ſtrictly required and commanded, and all who here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119796:4"/> ſhall be made Governors of any ſuch Iſlands, Plantations or Territories, by His Majeſty, His Heirs or Succeſſors, ſhall before their entrance into their Government take a Solemn Oath to do their utmoſt, that every the afore mentioned Clauſes, and all the matters and things therein contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſhall be punctually and <hi>bona fide</hi> obſerved, according to the true intent and meaning thereof: And upon complaint and proof made before His Majeſty, His Heirs or Succeſſors, or ſuch as ſhall be by Him or them thereunto Authorized and appointed, that any the ſaid Governors have been willingly and wittingly negligent in doing their duty ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, that the ſaid Governor ſo offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhall be removed from his Government.</p>
            <p>And it is further Enacted by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity aforeſaid, That no Goods or Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities whatſoever of the Growth, Producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Manufacture of <hi>Africa, Aſia,</hi> or <hi>Ameri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> or of any part thereof, or which are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed or laid down in the uſual Mans or Cards of thoſe Places, be imported into <hi>England, Ireland,</hi> or <hi>Wales,</hi> Iſlands of <hi>Guern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey</hi> or <hi>Jerſey,</hi> or Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> in any other Ship or Ships, Veſſel or Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels whatſoever, but in ſuch as do truly and without fraud belong onely to the people of <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> Dominion of <hi>Wales,</hi> or Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> or of the Lands, Iſlands, Plantations or Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in <hi>Aſia, Africa,</hi> or <hi>America</hi> to His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty belonging, as the Proprietors and right Owners thereof, and whereof the Maſter
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119796:4"/> and three Fourths at leaſt of the Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners are Engliſh, under the penalty of the forfeiture of all ſuch Goods and Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and of the Ship or Veſſel in which they were Imported, with all her Guns, Tackle, Furniture, Ammunition, and Apparel, one moyety to His Majeſty, His Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, and the other moyety to him or them who ſhall ſeize, inform, or ſue for the ſame in any Court of Record, by Bill, Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Plaint, or other Action, wherein no Eſſoign, Protection, or wager in Law ſhall be allowed.</p>
            <p>And it is further Enacted by the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty aforeſaid, That no Goods or Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that are of forain Growth, Producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Manufacture, and which are to be brought into <hi>England, Ireland, Wales,</hi> the Iſlands of <hi>Guernſey</hi> and <hi>Jerſey,</hi> or Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> in Engliſh-built ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, or other ſhipping belonging to ſome of the aforeſaid Places, and navigated by Engliſh Mariners as aboveſaid, ſhall be ſhipped or brought from any other Place or Places, Countrey or Countreys, but onely from thoſe of their ſaid Growth, Producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Manufacture, or from thoſe Ports where the ſaid Goods and Commodities can onely, or are, or uſually have been firſt ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for tranſportation, and from none other Places or Countreys, under the penalty of the forfeiture of all ſuch of the foreſaid Goods, as ſhall be Imported from any other Place or Countrey contrary to the true intent and meaning hereof, as alſo of the ſhip in which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119796:5"/> they were Imported, with all her Guns, Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture, Ammunition, Tackle and Apparel, one Moyety to His Majeſty, His Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, and the other Moyety to him or them that ſhall ſeize, inform or ſue for the ſame in any Court of Record to be recovered as is before expreſt.</p>
            <p>And it is further Enacted by the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty aforeſaid, That any ſort of Ling, Stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſh, Pilchard, or any other kinde of dryed or ſalted fiſh, uſually fiſhed for and caught by the people of <hi>England, Ireland, Wales,</hi> Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> or any ſort of Codfiſh or Herring, or any Oyl or Blubber, made or that ſhall be made of any kinde of Fiſh what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, or any Whale-fins or Whale-bones, which ſhall be imported into <hi>England, Ireland, Wales,</hi> or Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> not having been caught in veſſels truly and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly belonging thereunto as Proprietors and right Owners thereof, and the ſaid Fiſh cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſaved or dryed, and the Oyl and Blubber aforeſaid (which ſhall be accompted and pay as Oyl) not made by the people thereof, and ſhall be imported into <hi>England, Ireland,</hi> or <hi>Wales,</hi> or Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> ſhall pay double Aliens Cuſtom.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity aforeſaid, That from henceforth it ſhall not be lawful to any Perſon or Perſons whatſoever, to Load or cauſe to be Loaden and carried in any Bottom or Bottoms, Ship or Ships, Veſſel or Veſſels whatſoever, whereof any Stranger or Strangers born (unleſs ſuch as be Denizens or Naturalized)
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119796:5"/> be Owners, Part-owners, or Maſter, and whereof three fourths of the Mariners at leaſt ſhall not be <hi>Engliſh,</hi> any Fiſh, Victual, Wares, Goods, Commodities, or things of what kinde or nature ſoever the ſame ſhall be, from one Port or Creek of <hi>England, Ireland, Wales, Iſlands</hi> of <hi>Guernſey</hi> or <hi>Jerſey,</hi> or Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> to another Port or Creek of the ſame or of any of them, under penalty for every one that ſhall offend con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the true meaning of this branch of this preſent Act, to forfeit all ſuch goods as ſhall be loaden and carried in any ſuch Ship or Veſſel, together with the Ship or Veſſel, and all her Guns, Ammunition, Tackle, Furniture and Apparel, one Moyety to His Majeſty his Heirs and Succeſſors, and the other Moyety to him or them that ſhall In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, Seiſe or Sue for the ſame in any Court of Record to be recovered in maner afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
            <p>And it is further Enacted by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity a foreſaid, That where any Eaſe, Abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Priviledge is given in the Book of Rates to goods or Commodities Imported or Exported in Engliſh built Shipping, that is to ſay, ſhipping built in <hi>England, Ireland, Wales,</hi> Iſlands of <hi>Guernſey</hi> or <hi>Jerſey,</hi> or Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> or in any the Lands, Iſlands, Dominions or Territories to His Majeſty in <hi>Africa, Aſia</hi> or <hi>America</hi> belonging or in his poſſeſſion, That it is always to be underſtood, and provided that the Maſter and three fourths of the Mariners of the ſaid ſhips, at leaſt, be alſo Engliſh; And that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119796:6"/> where it is required that the Maſter and three Fourths of the Mariners be Engliſh, that the true intent and meaning thereof is, that they ſhould be ſuch during the whole voyage, unleſs in caſe of ſickneſs, death, or being taken Priſoners in the voyage, to be proved by the Oath of the Maſter or other chief Officer of ſuch ſhips.</p>
            <p>And it is further Enacted by the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty aforeſaid, That no goods or Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the growth, production or manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of <hi>Muſcovy,</hi> or of any the Countreys, Dominions or Territories to the great Duke or Emperor of <hi>Muſcovy</hi> or <hi>Ruſſia</hi> belonging, As alſo that no ſorts of Maſts, Timber or Boards, no forein Salt, Pitch, Tar, Rozin, Hemp or Flax, Raizins, Figs, Prunes, Olive Oyls, no ſorts of Corn or Grayn, Sugar, Pot-aſhes, Wines, Vinegar, or Spirits called Aquavite or Brandy wine, ſhall from &amp; after the firſt day of <hi>April,</hi> which ſhall be in the year of our Lord One thouſand ſix hundred ſixty one, be imported into <hi>England, Ireland, Wales</hi> or Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed</hi> in any ſhip or ſhips, veſſel or veſſels whatſoever, but in ſuch as do truly and without fraud belong to the people thereof, or of ſome of them as the true Owners and Proprietors thereof, and whereof the Maſter and three Fourths of the Mariners at leaſt are Engliſh, and that no Currants nor Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of the growth, production or manufacture of any the Countreys, Iſlands, Dominions or Territories to the <hi>Othoman</hi> or Turkiſh Empire belonging, ſhall from
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119796:6"/> and after the firſt day of <hi>September</hi> which ſhall be in the year of our Lord One thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſix hundred ſixty one, be imported into any the forementioned places in any ſhip or veſſel, but which is of Engliſh built and Navigated as aforeſaid, and in no other; Except onely ſuch forain ſhips and veſſels as are of the built of that Countrey or place of which the ſaid Goods are the growth, production or manufacture reſpectively, or of ſuch Port where the ſaid Goods can onely be, or moſt uſually are firſt ſhipped for tranſportation, and whereof the Maſter and three Fourths of the Mariners at leaſt are of the ſaid Countrey or place, under the penalty and forfeiture of ſhip and Goods to be diſpoſed and recovered as in the foregoing Clauſe.</p>
            <p>Provided always, and be it hereby En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted by the Authority aforeſaid, That for the prevention of the great frauds daily uſed in colouring and concealing of Aliens Goods, all Wines of the growth of <hi>France</hi> or <hi>Germany,</hi> which from and after the Twentieth day of <hi>October</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred ſixty, ſhall be Imported into any the Ports or places aforeſaid, in any other ſhip or veſſel then which doth truly and without fraud belong to <hi>England, Ireland, Wales,</hi> or Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> and Navigated with the Mariners there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of as aforeſaid, ſhall be deemed Aliens Goods, and pay all Strangers Cuſtoms and duties to His Majeſty, His Heirs and Succeſſors, as alſo to the Town or
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119796:7"/> Port, into which they ſhall be Imported; And that all ſorts of Maſts, Timber or Boards, as alſo all forain Salt, Pitch, Tar, Rozin, Hemp, Flax, Raizins, Figs, Prunes, Olive Oyls, all ſorts of Corn or Grain, Sugar, Pot-aſhes, Spirits commonly called Brandy wine or Aquavite, Wines of the growth of Spain, the Iſlands of the <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> or <hi>Portugal, Madera</hi> or Weſtern Iſlands, and all Goods of the growth, production or manufacture of <hi>Moſcovy</hi> or <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> which from and after the Firſt day of <hi>April</hi> which ſhall be in the year of our Lord One thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſix hundred ſixty one, ſhall be Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into any of the aforeſaid places in any other then ſuch ſhipping, and ſo Navigated, and all Currants and Turky Commodities which from and after the Firſt day of <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred ſixty one, ſhall be Imported into any the places aforeſaid, in any other then Engliſh built ſhipping and Navigated as aforeſaid, ſhall be deemed Aliens Goods, and pay according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to His Majeſtie, His Heirs and Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, and to the Town or Port into which they ſhall be Imported.</p>
            <p>And for prevention of all Frauds which may be uſed in colouring or buying of Forain Ships, Be it Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, and it is hereby Enacted, That from and after the Firſt day of <hi>April,</hi> which ſhall be in the year of our Lord One thouſand ſix hundred ſixty one, no Forain built Ship or Veſſel whatſoever ſhall be deemed or paſs as a Ship to <hi>England, Ireland, Wales,</hi> or Town
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119796:7"/> of <hi>Berwick,</hi> or any of them belonging, or enjoy the benefit or priviledge of ſuch a Ship or Veſſel, until ſuch time that he or they claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſaid Ship or Veſſel to be theirs, ſhall make appear to the chief Officer or Officers of the Cuſtoms in the Port next to the place of his or their aboad, that he or they are not Aliens, and ſhall have taken an Oath before ſuch chief Officer or Officers, who are hereby Authorized to adminiſter the ſame, That ſuch Ship or Veſſel was <hi>bona fide</hi> and without fraud by him or them bought for a valuable conſideration, expreſſing the ſum, as alſo the time, place, and perſons from whom it was bought, and who are his part-owners (if he have any) all which part-owners ſhall be lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid Oath before the chief Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer or Officers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cuſtom-houſe of the Port next to the place of their aboad, and that no Forainer directly or indirectly hath any part, intereſt, or ſhare therein, and that upon ſuch Oath he or they ſhall receive a Certificate under the Hand or Seal of the ſaid chief Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer or Officers of the Port where ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons ſo making Oath do reſide, whereby ſuch Ship or Veſſel may for the future paſs and be deemed as a Ship belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſaid Port, and enjoy the priviledge of ſuch a Ship or Veſſel; And the ſaid Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer or Officers ſhall keep a Regiſter of all ſuch Certificates as he or they ſhall ſo give, and return a Duplicat thereof to the chief Officers of the Cuſtoms at <hi>London</hi> for ſuch as ſhall be granted in <hi>England, Wales,</hi> and <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick,</hi> and to the chief Officers of the Cuſtoms
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119796:8"/> at <hi>Dublin</hi> for ſuch as ſhall be given in <hi>Ireland,</hi> together with the Names of the perſon or perſons from whom ſuch Ship was bought, and the ſum of Money which was paid for her, as alſo the Names of all ſuch perſons who are part-owners of her, if any ſuch be.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity aforeſaid, That if any Officer of the Cuſtoms ſhall from and after the ſaid Firſt day of <hi>April,</hi> allow the priviledge of being a Ship or Veſſel to <hi>England, Ireland, Wales,</hi> or Town of <hi>Berwick,</hi> or any of them belonging, to any Forain built Ship or Veſſel, until ſuch Certificate be before them produced, or ſuch Proof and Oath taken before them; or if any Officer of the Cuſtoms ſhall allow the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of an Engliſh built Ship, or other Ship to any the aforeſaid places belonging to any Engliſh or Forain built Ship coming into any Port, and making Entry of any Goods, until Examination whether the Maſter and three fourths of the Mariners be Engliſh, or ſhall allow to any Forain built Ship, bringing in the Commodities of the Growth of the Countrey where it was built, the priviledge by this Act to ſuch ſhip given, until Examination and Proof whether it be a ſhip of the built of that Countrey, and that the Maſter and three fourths of the Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners are of that Countrey; or if any perſon who is or ſhall be made Governor of any Lands, Iſlands, Plantations, or Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in <hi>Africa, Aſia,</hi> or <hi>America,</hi> by His Majeſty, His Heirs or Succeſſors, ſhall ſuffer any Forain built Ship or Veſſel to load or unload
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119796:8"/> any Goods or Commodities within the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cincts of their Governments, until ſuch Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificate be produced before them or ſuch as ſhall be by them appointed to view the ſame, and Examination whether the Maſter and three fourths of the Mariners at leaſt be Engliſh, that for the firſt Offence ſuch Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer of the Cuſtoms and Governors ſhall be put out of their Places, Officers or Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>Provided always, That this Act or any thing therein contained, extend not, or be meant to reſtrain and prohibite the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of any the Commodities of the <hi>Straights,</hi> or <hi>Levant</hi> Seas, loaden in Engliſh built ſhipping, &amp; whereof the Maſter &amp; three fourths of the Mariners at leaſt are Engliſh, from the uſual Ports or Places for lading of them heretofore within the ſaid <hi>Straights</hi> or <hi>Levant</hi> Seas, though the ſaid Commodities be not of the very Growth of the ſaid places.</p>
            <p>Provided alſo, That this Act, or any thing therein contained, extend not, or be meant to reſtrain the Importing of any <hi>Eaſt India</hi> Commodities, loaden in Engliſh built ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and whereof the Maſter and three fourths of the Mariners at leaſt are Engliſh, from the uſual place or places for lading of them in any part of thoſe Seas, to the South-ward and Eaſt-ward of <hi>Cabo bona ſperanza,</hi> although the ſaid Ports be not the very Places of their Growth.</p>
            <p>Provided alſo, That it ſhall and may be lawful to and for any of the people of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Ireland, Wales,</hi> Iſlands of <hi>Guernſey</hi> or
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119796:9"/> 
               <hi>Jerſey,</hi> or Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> in Veſſels or Ships to them belonging, and whereof the Maſter and three fourths of the Mariners at leaſt are Engliſh, to load and bring in from any of the Ports of <hi>Spain</hi> or <hi>Portugal,</hi> or Weſtern Iſlands, commonly called <hi>Azores,</hi> or <hi>Madera,</hi> or <hi>Canary</hi> Iſlands, all ſorts of Goods or Commodities of the Growth, Production, or Manufacture of the Plantations or Dominions of either of them reſpectively.</p>
            <p>Provided, That this Act, or any thing therein contained, extend not to Bullion, nor yet to any Goods taken, or that ſhall be <hi>bona fide</hi> taken by way of Repriſal by any Ship or Ships belonging to <hi>England, Ireland,</hi> or <hi>Wales,</hi> Iſlands of <hi>Guernſey</hi> or <hi>Jerſey,</hi> or Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> and whereof the Maſter and three fourths of the Mariners at leaſt are Engliſh, having Commiſſion from His Majeſty, His Heirs or Succeſſors.</p>
            <p>Provided always, That this Act, or any thing therein contained, ſhall not extend, or be conſtrued to extend to lay Aliens Duties upon any Corn of the Growth of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or to any Salt made in <hi>Scotland,</hi> nor to any Fiſh caught, ſaved and cured by the people of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and Imported directly from <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in Scotch built Ships, and whereof the Maſter and three fourths of the Mariners are of His Majeſties Subjects, nor to any Seal Oyl of <hi>Ruſsia,</hi> Imported from thence into <hi>England, Ireland, Wales,</hi> or Town of <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> in ſhipping <hi>bona fide</hi> to ſome of the ſaid places belonging, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119796:9"/> the Maſter and three fourths of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners at leaſt are Engliſh.</p>
            <p>Provided alſo, and it is hereby Enacted, That every Ship or Veſſel belonging to any the Subjects of the French King, which from and after the Twentieth day of <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> in the year of our Lord One thouſand ſix hundred and ſixty, ſhall come into any Port, Creek, Harbor or Road of <hi>England, Ireland, Wales,</hi> or Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> and ſhall there lade or unlade any Goods or Commodities, or take in or ſet on ſhore any paſſengers, ſhall pay to the Collector of His Majeſties Cuſtoms in ſuch Port, Creek, Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor or Road, for every Tun of which the ſaid Ship or Veſſel is of burthen, to be computed by ſuch Officer of the Cuſtoms as ſhall be thereunto appointed, the ſum of Five ſhillings currant Money of <hi>England:</hi> And that no ſuch Ship or Veſſel be ſuffered to depart out of ſuch Port, Creek, Harbor or Road, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the ſaid Duty be fully paid; And that this Duty ſhall continue to be Collected, Levied, and Paid for ſuch time, as a certain Duty of Fifty Solls <hi>per</hi> Tun, lately impoſed by the French King, or any part thereof, ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to be Collected upon the ſhipping of <hi>England</hi> lading in <hi>France,</hi> and three Moneths after, and no longer.</p>
            <p>And it is further Enacted by the Authority aforeſaid, That from and after the Firſt day of <hi>April,</hi> which ſhall be in the year of our Lord One thouſand ſix hundred ſixty one, no Sugars, Tobacco, Cotton-wooll, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicoes, Ginger, Fuſtick, or other dying wood, of the Growth, Production or Manufacture
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119796:10"/> of any Engliſh Plantations in <hi>America, Aſia,</hi> or <hi>Africa,</hi> ſhall be ſhipped, carried, conveyed or tranſported from any of the ſaid Engliſh Plantations to any Land, Iſland, Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, Dominion, Port, or Place whatſoever, other then to ſuch other Engliſh Plantations as do belong to His Majeſty, His Heirs and Succeſſors, or to the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> or <hi>Ireland<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> or Principality of <hi>Wales,</hi> or Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> there to be laid on ſhore, under the penalty of the forfeiture of the ſaid Goods or the full value thereof, as alſo of the Ship with all her Guns, Tackle, Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel, Ammunition and Furniture, The one moyety to the Kings Majeſty, His Heirs and Succeſſors, and the other moyety to him or them that ſhall ſeize, inform, or ſue for the ſame in any Court of Record, by Bill, Plaint or Information, wherein no Eſſoign, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, or wager of Law ſhall be allowed.</p>
            <p>And be it further Enacted by the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty aforeſaid, That for every Ship or Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, which from and after the Five and twentieth day of <hi>December,</hi> in the year of our Lord One thouſand ſix hundred and ſixty, ſhall ſet ſail out of or from <hi>England, Ireland, Wales,</hi> or Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> for any Engliſh Plantation in <hi>America, Aſia,</hi> or <hi>Africa,</hi> ſufficient bond ſhall be given with one ſurety to the chief Officers of the Cuſtom-houſe of ſuch Port or Place from whence the ſaid Ship ſhall ſet ſail, to the value of One thouſand pounds, if the Ship be of leſs bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then then one hundred Tuns; and of the ſum of Two thouſand pounds, if the Ship ſhall be of greater burthen, That in caſe the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119796:10"/> ſaid Ship or Veſſel ſhall load any of the ſaid Commodities at any of the ſaid Engliſh Plantations, that the ſame Commodities ſhall be by the ſaid ſhip brought to ſome Port of <hi>England, Ireland, Wales,</hi> or to the Port or Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> and ſhall there unload and put on ſhore the ſame, the danger of the ſeas onely excepted: And for all ſhips coming from any other Port or Place to any of the aforeſaid Plantations, who by this Act are permitted to Trade there, that the Governor of ſuch Engliſh Plantations ſhall before the ſaid ſhip or veſſel be permitted to load on board any of the ſaid Commodities, take Bond in maner and to the value aforeſaid for each reſpective ſhip or veſſel, That ſuch ſhip or veſſel ſhall carry all the aforeſaid Goods that ſhall be laden on board in the ſaid ſhip to ſome other of His Majeſties Engliſh Plantations, or to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Ireland, Wales,</hi> or Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed:</hi> And that every ſhip or veſſel, which ſhall load or take on board any of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Goods, until ſuch Bond given to the ſaid Governor, or Certificate produced from the Officers of any Cuſtom-houſe of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Ireland, Wales,</hi> or of the Town of <hi>Berwick,</hi> that ſuch Bond have been there duly given, ſhall be forfeited with all her Guns, Tackle, Apparel and Furniture, to be imployed and recovered in maner as aforeſaid. And the ſaid Governors and every of them ſhall twice in every year after the Firſt day of <hi>January,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred and ſixty, return true Copies of all ſuch Bonds by him ſo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, to the chief Officers of the Cuſtom in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119796:11"/>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:119796:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Anno Regni CAROLI II. AN ACT To Prevent FRAUDS AND CONCEALMENTS OF His Majeſties CUSTOMS and SUBSIDIES.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>E it Enacted by the Kings moſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Majeſty, by and with the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and conſent of the Lords and Commons in this preſent Parliament Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119796:12"/> That if any perſon or perſons at any time after the Firſt day of <hi>September,</hi> One thouſand ſix hundred and ſixty, ſhall cauſe any Goods for which Cuſtom, Subſidy, or other Duties are due, or payable by vertue of the Act paſſed this Parliament, (Entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>A Subſidie granted to the King of Tonnage and Poundage, and other ſums of Money, payable up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Merchandize Exported and Imported</hi>) to be landed or conveyed away without due entry thereof firſt made, and the Cuſtomer or Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector, or his Deputy agreed with, That then and in ſuch caſe upon Oath thereof made before the Lord Treaſurer, or any of the Barons of the Exchequer, or chief Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate of the Port or Place where the offence ſhall be committed, or the Place next ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning thereunto, it ſhall be lawful to and for the Lord Treaſurer, or any of the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons aforeſaid, or chief Magiſtrate of the Port or Place where the offence ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, or the Place next adjoyning there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, to iſſue out a Warrant to any perſon or perſons, thereby enabling him or them with the aſſiſtance of a Sheriff, Iuſtice of Peace, or Conſtable to enter into any Houſe in the day time where ſuch Goods are ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to be concealed; and in caſe of reſiſtance to break open ſuch Houſes, and to ſeize and ſecure the ſame Goods ſo concealed: And all Officers and Miniſters of Iuſtice are hereby required to be aiding and aſſiſting thereunto.</p>
            <p>Provided always, That no Houſe ſhall be entred by vertue of this Act, unleſs it be within the ſpace of one Moneth after the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119796:12"/> offence ſuppoſed to be committed.</p>
            <p>Provided alſo, That this Act ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in force unto the end of the Firſt Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the next Parliament, and no longer.</p>
            <p>Provided alſo, That if the Information whereupon any Houſe ſhall come to be ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſhall prove to be falſe, that then and in ſuch caſe the party injured ſhall recover his full Damages and Coſts againſt the Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, by action of Treſpaſs to be therefore brought againſt ſuch Informer.</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
